I have spent the past few years putting myself into situations that are usually very difficult
and at the same time somewhat dangerous.
I went to prison, difficult.
I worked in a coal mine, dangerous.
I filmed in war zones, difficult and dangerous.
And I spent 30 days eating nothing but this, fun in the beginning, little difficult in
the middle, very dangerous in the end.
In fact, most of my career I have been immersing myself into seemingly horrible situations
for the whole goal of trying to examine societal issues in a way that make them engaging, that
make them interesting, that hopefully break them down in a way that make them entertaining
and accessible to an audience.
So when I knew I was coming here to do a TED Talk that was going to look at the world of
branding and sponsorship, I knew I would want to do something a little different.
So as some of you may or may not have heard, a couple weeks ago I took out an ad on eBay.
I sent out some Facebook messages, some Twitter messages, and I gave people the opportunity
to buy the naming rights to my 2011 TED Talk.
That's right, some lucky individual, corporation, for-profit or non-profit, was going to get
the once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, because I'm sure Chris Anderson will never let it
happen again, to buy the naming rights to the talk you're watching right now, that at
the time didn't have a title, didn't really have a lot of content, and didn't really give
much hint as to what the subject matter would actually be.
So what you were getting was this.
Your name here presents my TED Talk, that you have no idea what the subject is and depending
on the content could ultimately blow up in your face, especially if I make you or your
company look stupid for doing it.
But that being said, it's a very good media opportunity.
You know how many people watch these TED Talks, it's a lot.
That's just a working title by the way.
So even with that caveat, I knew that someone would buy the naming rights.
Now if you'd have asked me that a year ago, I wouldn't have been able to tell you that
with any certainty, but in the new project that I'm working on, my new film, we examine
the world of marketing, advertising, and as I said earlier, I put myself in some pretty
horrible situations over the years, but nothing could prepare me, nothing could ready me for
anything as difficult or as dangerous as going into the rooms with these guys.
You see, I had this idea for a movie.
What I want to do is make a film all about product placement, marketing, and advertising,
where the entire film is funded by product placement, marketing, and advertising.
So the movie will be called The Greatest Movie Ever Sold.
So what happens in The Greatest Movie Ever Sold is that everything from top to bottom,
from start to finish, is branded from beginning to end.
From the above the title sponsor that you'll see in the movie, which is Brand X.
Now this brand, the Qualcomm Stadium, the Staples Center, these people will be married
to the film In Perpetuity Forever, and so the film explores this whole idea.
It's what?
In Perpetuity Forever.
I'm a redundant person.
I'm just saying.
That was more in perpetuity, period, forever, but not only are we going to have the Brand
X title sponsor, but we're going to make sure we sell out every category we can in the film.
So maybe we sell a shoe and it becomes the greatest shoe you ever wore, the greatest
car you ever drove from The Greatest Movie Ever Sold, you know, the greatest drink you've
ever had, courtesy of The Greatest Movie Ever Sold.
So the idea is, beyond just showing that brands are part of your life, but actually get them
to finance the film?
Get them to finance the film, and actually we show the whole process of how does it work.
The goal of this whole film is transparency.
You're going to see the whole thing take place in this movie.
So that's the whole concept, the whole film, start to finish, and I would love for CEG
to help make it happen.
Yeah, you know, it's funny because when I first hear it, it is the ultimate respect
for an audience.
I don't know how receptive people are going to be to it, though.
Do you have a perspective, or do you, I don't want to use angle because that sort of has
a negative connotation, but do you sort of know how this is going to play out?
No idea.
How much money does it take to do this?
1.5 million.
Good, good.
I think that you're going to have a hard time meeting with them, but I think it's certainly
worth pursuing a couple of really big, obvious brands.
Who knows?
Maybe by the time your film comes out, we look like a bunch of blithering idiots.
What do you think the response is going to be?
The response is mostly will be no.
But is the toughest sell because of the film, or is the toughest sell because of me?
Both.
That meaning, not so optimistic.
So, sir, can you help me?
I need help.
I can help.
Okay.
Good.
Awesome.
We've got to figure out which brands.
Yeah.
That's the challenge.
When you look at the people you deal with.
We've got some places we can go.
Okay.
Turn the camera off.
I thought turn the camera off meant let's have an off-the-record conversation.
Turns out it really means we want nothing to do with your movie.
And just like that, one by one, all of these companies suddenly disappeared.
None of them wanted anything to do with this movie.
I was amazed.
They wanted absolutely nothing to do with this project.
I was blown away because I thought the whole concept, the idea of advertising, was to get
your product out in front of as many people as possible, to get to as many people to see
it as possible.
Especially in today's world, this intersection of new media and old media and the fractured
media landscape isn't the idea to get that new buzzworthy delivery vehicle that's going
to get that message to the masses.
That's what I thought.
But the problem was, you see, my idea had one fatal flaw.
And that flaw was this.
Actually, no, that was not the flaw whatsoever.
That wouldn't have been a problem at all.
See, this would have been fine.
But what this image represents was the problem.
See, when you do a Google image search for transparency, this is one of the first images
that comes up.
So I like the way you roll, Sergey Brin.
No.
This, this was the problem, transparency.
Free from pretense or deceit, easily detected or seen through, readily understood, characterized
by visibility or accessibility of information, especially concerning business practices.
That last line being probably the biggest problem.
You see, we hear a lot about transparency these days.
Our politicians say it, our president says it, even our CEOs say it.
But suddenly when it comes down to it becoming a reality, something suddenly changes.
But why?
Well, transparency is scary.
Like that odd still screaming bear.
It's unpredictable.
Like this odd country road.
And it's also very risky.
What else is?
What else is risky?
Eating an entire bowl of Cool Whip.
That's very risky.
No, when I started talking to companies, you know, and telling them, you know, we wanted
to tell this story and they said, no, we want you to tell a story.
We want you to tell a story.
But we just want to tell our story.
See, when I was a kid and my father would catch me in some sort of a lie, there he is
giving me the look he often gave me, he would say, son, there's three sides to every story.
There's your story.
There's my story.
And there's the real story.
Now, you see, with this film, we wanted to tell the real story.
But with only one company, one agency willing to help me, and that's only because I knew
John Bond and Richard Kirshenbaum for years, I realized that I would have to go on my own.
I'd have to cut out the middleman and go to the companies myself, you know, myself with
all of my team.
So, what you suddenly started to realize, or what I started to realize, is that when
you started having conversations with these companies, the idea of understanding your
brand is a universal problem.
I have friends who make great big giant Hollywood films, and I have friends who make little
independent films like I make.
And the friends of mine who make big giant Hollywood movies say that the reason their
films are so successful is because of the brand partners that they have.
And then my friends who make small independent films say, well, how are we supposed to compete
with these big giant Hollywood movies?
And the movie is called The Greatest Movie Ever Sold.
So, now how specifically will we see band in the film?
Anytime I'm getting ready to go, anytime I open up my medicine cabinet, you will see
band deodorant.
Well, anytime I do an interview with someone, I could say, are you fresh enough for this
interview?
Are you ready?
You look a little nervous.
I want to help you calm down, so maybe you should put some on for the interview.
So, we'll offer one of these fabulous sets, whether it's a floral fusion or a paradise
winds, you know, they'll have their chance.
We will have them geared for both male or female, you know, solid roll on her stick,
whatever it may be.
That's the two cent tour.
So, now I can answer any of your questions and give you the five cent tour.
We are a smaller brand, much like you talked about being a smaller, you know, movie, we're
very much a challenger brand, so we don't have the budgets that other brands have.
So, doing things like this, you know, remind people about band is kind of why we're interested
in it.
What are the words that you would use to describe band?
Band is blank.
Technology is not the way you want to describe something somebody's putting in their armpit.
We talk about bold, fresh, I think fresh is a great word that really spins this category
into the positive versus the fights odor and wetness.
Right.
It keeps you fresh.
How do we keep you fresher, longer, better freshness, more freshness?
Three times fresher, things like that that are, you know, more of that positive benefit.
And that's a multimillion dollar corporation.
What about me?
What about a regular guy?
I need to go talk to the man on the street.
The people who are like me, the regular Joes, they need to tell me about my brand.
How would you guys describe your brand?
My brand?
I don't know, like, I like really nice clothes.
80s revival meets skater punk, unless it's laundry day.
Right.
What is brand Jerry?
Unique.
I guess what kind of genre of style I am would be like dark glamour.
I like a lot of black colors, a lot of grays and stuff like that.
But usually I have an accessory like sunglasses or I like crystal and things like that, too.
If Dan were a brand, he might be a classic, convertible Mercedes Benz.
The brand that I am is, I would call it casual fly.
Part hippie, part yogi, part Brooklyn girl, I don't know.
I'm the pet guy.
I sell pet toys all over the country, all over the world.
So I guess that's my brand and my warped little industry.
That's my brand.
My brand is FedEx because I deliver the goods.
Failed writer alcoholic brand.
Is that something?
I'm a lawyer brand.
I'm Tom.
Well, we can't all be brand Tom, but I do often find myself at the intersection of dark
glamour and casual fly.
What I realized, I needed an expert.
I need somebody who could get inside my head, somebody who could really help me understand
what they call your brand personality.
And so I found a company called Olson's Altman in Pittsburgh, who they've helped companies
like Nestle, Febreze, Hallmark discover that brand personality.
If they could do it for them, surely they could do it for me.
You brought your pictures, right?
I did.
The very first picture is a picture of my family.
So tell me a little bit how it relates to your thoughts and feelings about who you are.
These are the people who shape the way I look at the world.
Tell me about this world.
This world?
Yeah.
I think your world is the world that you live in.
The people that are around you, your friends, your family, the way you live your life, the
job you do, all those things stemmed and started from one place, and for me, they stemmed and
started with my family in West Virginia.
What's the next one you want to talk about?
The next one, this is the best day ever.
How does this relate to thoughts and feelings about who you are?
It's like, who do I want to be?
I like things that are different.
I like things that are weird.
I like weird things.
Tell me about the Y phase.
What does that do for us?
What is the machete?
What pupa stage are you in now?
Why is it important to reboot?
What does the red represent?
Tell me a little bit about that heart.
Tell me a little bit about you that's not who you are now.
What are some other metamorphosis that you have?
You have to be feared.
What kind of roller coaster are you on?
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks for your patience.
Great job.
Yeah.
Thanks a lot.
All right.
Yeah.
I don't know what's going to come of this.
There was a whole lot of crazy going on in there.
The first thing we saw was this idea that you had two distinct but complementary sides
to your brand personality.
The Morgan Spurlock brand is a mindful play brand.
Those are juxtaposed very nicely together, and I think there's almost a paradox with
those.
I think some companies will just focus on one of their strengths or the other instead
of focusing on both.
Most companies tend to, it's human nature, to avoid things that they're not sure of,
avoid fear, those elements.
You really embrace those, and you actually turn them into positives for you.
It's a neat thing to see.
What other brands are like that?
The first one here is a classic Apple, and you can see here, too, Target, We, Mini from
Mini Coopers, and JetBlue.
There's playful brands and mindful brands, those sort of things that have come and gone,
but a playful, mindful brand is a pretty powerful thing.
A playful, mindful brand.
What is your brand?
If somebody asked you to describe your brand identity, your brand personality, what would
you be?
Are you an up attribute?
Are you something that gets the blood flowing?
Are you more of a down attribute?
Are you something that's a little more calm, reserved, conservative?
Up attributes are things like being playful, being fresh, like the Fresh Prince, contemporary,
adventurous, edgy or daring like Errol Flynn, nimble or agile, profane, domineering, magical
or mystical like Gandalf.
Are you more of a down attribute?
Are you mindful, sophisticated like 007?
Are you established, traditional, nurturing, protective, empathetic like the Oprah?
Are you reliable, stable, familiar, safe, secure, sacred, contemplative or wise like
the Dalai Lama or Yoda?
Over the course of this film, we had 500 plus companies who were up and down companies say
no, they didn't want any part of this project.
They wanted nothing to do with this film, mainly because they had no control.
They would have no control over the final product, but we did get 17 brand partners
who were willing to relinquish that control, who wanted to be in business with someone
as mindful and as playful as myself, and who ultimately empowered us to tell stories
that normally we wouldn't be able to tell, stories that an advertiser would normally
never get behind.
They enabled us to tell the story about neuromarketing as we got into telling the story in this film
about how now they're using MRIs to target the desire centers of your brain for both
commercials as well as movie marketing.
We went to San Paolo where they have banned outdoor advertising in the entire city.
For the past five years, there's no billboards, there's no posters, there's no flyers, nothing.
And we went to school districts where now companies are making their way into cash-strapped
schools all across America.
What's incredible for me is the projects that I've gotten the most feedback out of, or I've
had the most success, and are ones where I've interacted with things directly.
And that's what these brands did.
They cut out the middleman.
They cut out their agencies and said, maybe these agencies don't have my best interests
in mind.
I'm going to deal directly with the artist.
I'm going to work with him to create something different, something that's going to get people
thinking, that's going to challenge the way we look at the world.
And how has that been for them?
Has it been successful?
Well, since the film premiered at the Sundance Film Festival, let's just take a look.
According to Burrells, the movie premiered in January, and since then, and this isn't
even the whole thing, we've had more than 900 million media impressions for this film.
That's literally covering just like a two and a half week period.
That's only online, no print, no TV.
The film hasn't even been distributed yet.
It's not even online.
It's not even streaming.
It's not even been out into other foreign countries yet.
So ultimately, this film has already started to gain a lot of momentum, and not bad for
a project that almost every ad agency we talk to advise their clients not to take part.
What I always believe is that if you take chances, if you take risks, that in those
risks will come opportunity.
I believe that when you push people away from that, you're pushing them more towards failure.
I believe that when you train your employees to be risk averse, then you're preparing your
whole company to be reward challenged.
I feel like that what has to happen moving forward is we need to encourage people to
take risks.
We need to encourage people to not be afraid of opportunities that may scare them.
Ultimately, moving forward, I think we have to embrace fear.
We've got to put that bear in a cage.
Embrace fear.
Embrace risk.
One big spoonful at a time, we have to embrace risk, and ultimately, we have to embrace transparency.
Today, more than ever, a little honesty is going to go a long way.
And that being said, through honesty and transparency, my entire talk, Embrace Transparency, has
been brought to you by my good friends at EMC, who for $7,100 bought the naming rights
on eBay, EMC turning big data into big opportunity for organizations all over the world.
EMC presents Embrace Transparency.
Thank you very much, guys.
Thank you.
So Morgan, in the name of transparency, what exactly happened to that $7,100?
That is a fantastic question.
I have in my pocket a check made out to the parent organization of the TED Foundation,
the Sapling Foundation, a check for $7,100 to be applied towards my attendance for next
year's TED.